[SPEAKER_01]: Inayantini mey jindu nangwa yinbatitni hako bachis
[SPEAKER_00]: So the arisal of a particular thought is not an integral part or an inherent part.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not one and the same, if you will, with the natural state of mind itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if a thought isn't an inherently existent part of one's mind, then its ending or its cessation can similarly not be an integral or inherent part of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, what to talk about is its remaining.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then the question is, do thoughts not exist at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: They exist but they don't truly exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, for example, when we think about then the way that there is no inherent arising or cessation of thoughts integral to then the nature of one's mind, then with regard to mind itself, mind itself cannot be neither benefited nor harmed by the arisal or then the cessation of these seemingly tangible, seemingly integral paths
[SPEAKER_00]: of our being, of these thoughts, if you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, we can notice the thoughts arising then, but then they will have no effect on our true nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, the advice is given then to simply rest in the true nature of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: This then is the experience of the bare natural state, the way it is now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you take that empty awareness that is open and carefree as the path,
[SPEAKER_00]: All the time, both during formal meditation practice and also afterward, in the post-meditation time, you will quickly and surely acquire a confident realization that confusion is freed by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here then, there are two things to bear in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the empty kind of awareness, that is then the formal kind of meditation practice, if you will, simply to remain within that bare natural state the way it is, open and carefree, and that's our kind of spiritual path, if you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to post-meditation period,
[SPEAKER_00]: the afterward, if you will, of the formal meditation practice, then it is essential to, at all times and in all situations, as much as one is possible, to look at then the nature of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look at when thoughts arise, to simply look at their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is similar then to the formal meditation practice, where one sustains the empty awareness, the nature of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So as such, during the post-meditation period, as much as one is able, one looks at the nature
[SPEAKER_00]: of one's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So something to do when you get stuck in the New York traffic.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm not really joking here.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're stuck in the New York traffic, or when you're in an elevator, or when you're on a bus, when you're travelling on an aeroplane etc, it's very easy simply to look within, to look at the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, when I say meditate like this, to look within, to look at the nature of mind, I'm not suggesting that you have to try to sit cross-legged and straighten your spine and put your hands in the meditation posture, etc.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here one just simply looks within.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, mention is made here then, that if you quickly, if you continue this practice as much as you're able,
[SPEAKER_00]: putting a great deal of effort into it, then you will quickly and surely acquire a confident realization that confusion then is freed by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the confusion then of grasping at the seemingly true existence of things will naturally be set free by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is very helpful then, we read, to mingle your mind inseparably with your teachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: By settling in equipoise within that state, developing faith and devotion, you will meet the natural face of Dharmakaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always tell some kind of newcomer who never had an opportunity to meet, like my lineage, from my lineage, it's like Japji Khyentse Rinpoche, of course different lineage, they all have very realized master.
[SPEAKER_01]: So those who didn't have opportunity to meet those masters, so I always say, when you say this mix,
[SPEAKER_01]: mingle your mind with Guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: To my people who come to me and my friends, I always recommend, because physically now, not there, but like in the movie, Dalai Lama said, spiritual energy or whatever, the lineage is very much alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we can always have this kind of Guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think it's really necessary to have someone who's physically there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So to give teaching, to transmit lineage, okay, younger lamas, lineage holders can do, but the root guru or source of inspiration, from my lineage, like Chabuji Kenser Rinpoche, I always say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, nowadays, thanks to the modern technology, we have a lot of videos, photos, we know how they look like, we know how they sound like, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So very much, we can still connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: someone like Longchenpa, Jimmy Lingpa or these great masters, we don't have much idea how, unless looking at the painting Thangka.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Thangka also, each one looks different.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now we have this photos and videos, I think very helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, spiritually, still not life, doesn't matter, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like His Holiness Dalai Lama says, spiritual energy is very much life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lineage is very much life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can get the instructions, teachings, empowerment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also inspiration like Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think also in Nyingma and Gaju tradition, maybe in other tradition also, but always there is end of the Guru Yoga, dissolving the three-syllable letters from Guru's forehead, Guru's throat, Guru's heart, syllable letter om, ah, hung, radiates three lights, dissolving into one's forehead, throat, and heart center, and then purifies our body, speech, mind, accumulating, purifies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then at the end, the three lights come, dissolve into one's forehead, throat and heart, and purifies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Subtle obscuration.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Guru dissolves into one's heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's where I think what we're describing here, mingle one's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So a little understanding, if you can gain from some practice or lots of meditating, then that moment, I think that's the time to sort of looking at the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have some experience, then understand that is what we call the Idam Guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: So within this, naturally feel very strong devotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is ultimate dharmakaya guru, or seeing the face of the dharmakaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that was English.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shall I say in Tibetan?
OK.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we should never kind of carry away in kind of high view.
[SPEAKER_01]: We should hear in the last sentence, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: meditate on impermanent, have a renunciation, and especially the conduct, law of the conduct, law of the karma, effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are an ordained monk or nun, then very strictly follow the Vinaya, law and conduct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then if you are a lay practitioner, I think the law of the karma we have to follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes the view is very high and then we jump in the view and then we fall down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think the view has to be vast and our conduct has to be very thoroughly, very fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, especially guard the continuity of impermanence, renunciation and pure discipline, like your own eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never diminish your one-pointed diligence in the heart of the matter, the essential yoga of profound meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, it is imperative at all times and in all situations to apply single-pointed diligence at the heart of the matter, to essentialize or to actualize this essential yoga of profound meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Khyentse Rinpoche always emphasizes on
[SPEAKER_01]: Thöpa means hearing the Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samba means contemplating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gompa means meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So always Khen Rinpoche recommends here also like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we should listen to Dharma, contemplate it, and then try to put into practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we just listen to so many Dharmas and then we don't contemplate, we don't think about, then it becomes my diet book.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have so many diet books and I'm still quite heavy.
[SPEAKER_01]: This I think happens quite a lot with some of what we call dharma bums.
[SPEAKER_01]: We collect so many books and attend all the teachings and our character never change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it's like my diet book.
[SPEAKER_01]: So maybe you don't need too many diet books, but one good diet book, and if you follow it, you will lose weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: May this delightful sacred offering cloud of essential pit instructions cause you to gain realization of the definitive secret that is like space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So here then, this is described as the kind of quintessence of the Dharma, the essential pit instructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think which is writing this to some kind of higher Lama, the way he described it, it's like an offering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you put this into practice then, this particular instruction, have engaged diligently, will cause you then to gain realization of the definitive secret which is likened here to space.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So what is it that you recognize when you recognize the nature of the mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's her question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know whether I have
[SPEAKER_01]: what you call, actualize, recognize or not, that's up to my teacher to decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: But normally we don't share that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think when you look at the sky, you say you see a sky, but what you really see is really right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some teachings say something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said he'll tell you later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rinpoche, here's another question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you have any advice on how to apply this practice to strong emotions?
[SPEAKER_02]: and sensations in the body, such as fear, same as thoughts or are they different?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is the strong emotion and this body sensation the same as a thought?
[SPEAKER_02]: Should it be dealt with the same as a thought or is it different?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think emotions
[SPEAKER_01]: It's part of what we call nam tok or thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we need a training.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think gomu, when you say gomu, it means familiarization, I think, literally translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the practice I think we have to get quite familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have to do again and again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you kind of get a little bit experience into resting in the state, nature of mind, then there will be less problem with all the, less problem which relate to with your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, emotion is also thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have some friends who didn't do much practice and then suddenly they had some emotional problem and then comes to me and say how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then it's difficult when you're already like ups and downs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think we have to
[SPEAKER_01]: when everything is sort of okay, we have to practice, practice, and once we really get quite familiar with this practice, then emotion will not bother so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: A good example is like riding a horse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you're very good at riding a horse,
[SPEAKER_01]: you become very balanced riding a horse, then no matter how much the horse jumps, it cannot throw you out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that previous training, and not without much previous training, you just ride on a wild horse and then you will be thrown out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It happened to me in Tibet once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think what we need is previously practice, practice, and then get familiar with it, and then naturally all the problems related with your mind will naturally be less and disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: This question is, if we let our thoughts and emotions just be,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, and we just stay and watch, does that mean we will then do nothing in life and be very passive or numb?
[SPEAKER_01]: Passive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Vegetable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a friend who, a friend told me a story.
[SPEAKER_01]: One guy went to see a doctor with a carrot in his nose and banana in his ear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he went to see a doctor and said, doctor I have a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And doctor says, yes you have an eating disorder.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think we are talking something like a vegetable, because when you talk about the meditation, there is a, I don't know how to describe in English, but I'm sure you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: many kind of where you can fall into.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore you need a good instruction, step by step we have to learn it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it could be sometimes ching wang, then maybe become vegetable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then mukpa, maybe you are sleeping.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are so many wrong you could go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this needs to be some skill master and then like guidance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when one begins to practice meditation, there are a number of erroneous paths that one can fall into.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's essential